Guide to the Office of Vice President for University Relations Records 1957-1962 RG 7.2.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of Vice President for University Relations
1957-1962
RG 7.2.1
New York University Archives
4.0 linear feet 4 linear feet (9 boxes)
The Office of the Vice President for University Relations was created in 1957 in response to the New York University Self-Study which recognized a need for coordination between the university and the community which it served. The Public Relations Department which oversaw the Office of Publication and Printing and Information Services was administratively transferred to the Vice President for University Relations when the new office was established. Arthur L. Brandon held the Office of Vice President for University Relations from 1957 through December 31, 1963. Arthur Leon Brandon had been Director of University Relations, a member of the public relations commission of the Association of American Colleges, and president of the American College Public Relations Association (ACPRA) from 1944 to 1946. The Office of the Vice President for University Relations was dissolved in 1965. These records include: correspondence, memoranda, press releases, reports, and minutes generated by the Office during Brandon's tenure.
New York University. Office of the Vice President for University Relations.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically except series III, which is arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
I, Adminstrative
II, Projects, Associations, Student Organizations & Informational
III, American College Public Relations Association
Scope and Content Note
This collection of records of the Office Of The Vice President for University Relations covers the period 1957 to 1962. Although Arthur L. Brandon officially held the office until December 31, 1963, there are no files for 1963.
The files in this record group represent the activities of Arthur L. Brandon from 1957 to 1962. There are a limited number of files which cover 1962 and no files for 1963.
The files contain correspondence and memoranda, press releases, reports, minutes of meetings, and carbon copies of letters and memoranda sent to Brandon for informational purposes. A significant amount of correspondence pertains to Brandon's membership in the American College Public Relations Association.
The collection had been considerably rearranged before this processing; a second rearrangement was undertaken during Fall 1986. The original transfile sheet mentioned in E. Frederic Knauth's Report to Chancellor Borowitz, 9/24/75 (Part I, No. 3), was missing.
Series I, Folder 17 contains correspondence regarding potential administrative posts at other universities for Executive Vice President John E. Ivey, Jr. as well as a letter from Ivey to Brandon outlining his reasons for resignation from NYU. There are also handwritten notes by Brandon regarding Ivey's resignation.
Series I, Folder 20 contains a copy of a memorandum from Executive Vice President Stoddard to President Hester recommending discontinuance of the Graduate Institute of Book Publishing.
Series I, Folder 24 includes an informational note: "8/60 - Inst. of XJ Economic Affairs - covering 1957 to Aug. 60 referred to vault. Retained some items in this file that might still be active."
Series I, Folder 33 contains correspondence with respect to President Newsom's participation in Look Magazine's Time Capsule deposited in a new office building in Des Moines, Iowa. The capsule, scheduled to be opened in 1987, included Newsom's predictions for higher education in the future.
Series I also contains a number of files dealing with NYU television programming. Cross-reference may be made to Record Group 6.0, Office of the Chancellor and/or Executive Vice President. These Ivey and Stoddard records also cover NYU's educational television development and programming.
Series II, Folders 81-82 contain correspondence and press statements regarding the strike of building service employees in February 1958 and that of food service employees in November 1958.
Series III, Folders 105-115 cover Brandon's participation as Program Chairman for the Washington, D.C. meeting of the American College Public Relations Association, July 11-13, 1960.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Office Of The Vice President for University Relations was created in 1957 in response to the New York University Self-Study which recognized a need for two-way communication between the university and the community which it served. The Self-Study, published in 1956, was financed by a grant from the Carnegie Corporation, and represented a major attempt at long-range planning under the leadership of then Chancellor Henry T. Heald. In the same year, a restructuring of administrative titles took place at NYU: the Chancellor became President and Vice Chancellors became Vice Presidents.
The new Vice President for University Relations became responsible for dissemination of information about New York University programs, and supervision of communication with the University community, and its neighbors through NYU's radio, television and publication units. During Chancellor Heald's administration (1952-56) the Public Relations Department had been responsible for the Office of Publication and Printing and for Information Services. The responsibility for these services was administratively transferred to the Vice President for University Relations when the new office was established and the directors of both units reported to him.
Arthur Leon Brandon came to New York University in 1957 from the University of Michigan where he had been Director of University Relations. A graduate of Broaddus College (now Alderson-Broaddus), Vice President Brandon held an M.A. from Bucknell University, an honorary degree of Doctor of Laws from Oklahoma Baptist University and an honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters was conferred by Alderson-Broaddus in 1962. He was a member of the public relations commission of the Association of American Colleges and was president of the American College Public Relations Association (ACPRA) from 1944 to 1946.
Arthur L. Brandon held the Office Of Vice President for University Relations through December 31, 1963. He was succeeded by Thomas P. Robinson on January 1, 1964. The office was dissolved in 1965.
Sources:
New York University, The New York University Self-Study Final Report (Washington Square, New York: New York University Press, 1956), p.4l4.
Handbook for Students At The Washington Square Center, New York University Bulletin Volume LVIII. Number 39, September 29,1958, pp. 15-16. Also, "Draft Copy" for Student Handbook-Directory. Arthur L. Brandon, Records Group 7.2.1., Series I, "Student Handbook-Directory" file.
New York University Official Directory 1963-1964, p. 5.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
Provenance
These records were transferred to the University Archives space in Room 500, 19 University Place from storage in Room SB-4 at Vanderbilt Hall in August 1975. A preliminary review was conducted by Dr. E. Frederick Knauth, Assistant Secretary of the University, in September 1975. These files constitute a portion of Record Group 7.2, Records of the Office Of Vice President for University Relations. The subject files which represent forty-five linear inches of processed material are arranged in three series and are contained in nine manuscript boxes. Each series is arranged alphabetically. Eleven inches of duplicate and published materials were removed. Fifty-three photographs were separated and will be added to the NYU Photo Collection. Four inches of material were discarded.
Alumni Federation of New York University, Inc.; American College Public Relations Association.; Brandon, Arthur L., (Arthur Leon); Heald, Henry T., (Henry Townly), 1904-1975; Ivey, John E., (John Eli), 1919-; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science.; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science.; New York University. History. 20th century.; New York University. Office of Public Affairs.; New York University. Office of the Vice President for University Relations.; New York University. School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance.; New York University. School of Education.; Robinson, Thomas P.; Correspondence.; Memorandums.; New York (State) |z New York.; Pamphlets.; Private universities and colleges |x Administration |y 20th century.; Universities and colleges |x Employees |x Labor unions.; Universities and colleges |x Faculty.; Universities and colleges |x Public relations.
- SERIES I: ADMINISTRATIVE
  - Admissions, Office of (T.P. Robinson, Director), 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Admissions, Office of (F.E. Crossland, Director), 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Federation, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Federation (Ross-Carlock Interim), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Federation (D. Robinson - L. Fertig Committee), 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Budget Office (Organization & Procedures), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Business Manager, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Center for Rehabilitation Services, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Commerce, School of, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Deans' Council (1), 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Deans' Council (2), 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deans' Faculty Meetings, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deans' Public Relations Meetings, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Development (Consultations with Robert Duncan - Kersting, Brown & Co., Inc.), 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Development (A. Crawford), 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Education, School of, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Executive Vice President, Office of (John E. Ivey, Jr.), 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fee Schedules 1958-60, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Graduate Arts & Science (Dean), 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Graduate Institute of Book Publishing, 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Graduate School of Public Administration, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Information Services, Office of, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Information Services, Monthly Reports, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Institute for Economic Affairs (Challenge), 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Metropolitan Educational TV Assn.(1), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Metropolitan Educational TV Assn.(2), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - New York State Dormitory Authority, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - NYU Club Public Relations Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Nuclear Development Corp., 1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Operation Scissors, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Personnel (Wm. Thaler, Director), 1957-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - President's Reports 1957-60, 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Public Relations Letters, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - RCA - Educational TV Workshops, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Radio - TV, Office of, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Students, Dean of (F. McCloskey), 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sunrise Semester, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Task Force Operations, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Television College of The Air, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer, Office of (Vice President for Business Affairs), 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Vice President and Secretary, Office of (Harold O. Voorhis), 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- SERIES II - PROJECTS, ASSOCIATIONS, STUDENT ORGANIZATIONS & INFORMATIONAL
  - African Fair, Inc., 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Air Pollution Project, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Federation Class of 1917, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - American Alumni Council, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Athletics - Baseball Playoffs, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Auxiliary Services (Grady E. Jensen), 1958-1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Benjamin Franklin Magazine Awards, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Blue Book (Enrollment Statistics), 1958 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Budget Forms U-M, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Businessman's Advisory Committee, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Center for Applied Social Research, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Christmas Messages, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Civil Defense, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Commencement 1959 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Commencement 1960 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Commencement 1961 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Congratulatory Letters, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - DGE "Maggie" Awards, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Enrollment Statistics, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Faculty Convocations 1957 & 1958 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Faculty Convocation 1959 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Federation of Undergraduate Student Councils (1), 1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Federation of Undergraduate Student Councils (2), 1958 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Foundation for Study of Cycles, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Fraternity Housing, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Gallatin Associates (1), 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Gallatin Associates (2), 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Harper & Brothers (Lecture-Publication Project), 1958 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Heald Report Correspondence, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Icelandic Committee, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Institute of Economic Affairs, 1957-1960 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Israel (Greidinger Report on Mission to), 1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Loeb Student Center, 1957-1960 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Loeb Student Center - Eisner & Lubin Dedication, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Medical Center (NYU Bellevue), 1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - NEA - Association for Higher Education, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Personnel - Absence Reports, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Public Relations Committee (University), 1957 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Public Relations Society of America, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Strike - Building Service Employees (Heights), 1958 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Strike - Food Services, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Student Activities Program (Summer 1959), 1958 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Student Handbook-Directory, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Student Organizations (Misc.), 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Systems, Planning and Procedures, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - TV (For Business & Industry [Commerce]}, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Television (Heights), 1958 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Tuition Evaluation Committee, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - U.S. Naval Supply Center, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - University Student Service Organization, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Urban Renewal, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Voorhis, Retirement Ceremonies, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Washington Square Promotion Contests, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 22)
- SERIES III: AMERICAN COLLEGE PUBLIC RELATIONS ASSOCIATION
  - ACPRA (Johnston & Ashmore Directorship), 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - ACPRA (Lyle Nelson, Pres.), 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - ACPRA - Denver Meeting, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - ACPRA - Educational Relations Round Table, 1960-1962 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - ACPRA - French Lick Meeting, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - ACPRA - Greenbrier Meeting, 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - ACPRA - Pittsburgh Meeting, 1957-1960 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - ACPRA - San Francisco Meeting, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - ACPRA - Sioux City Meeting, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - ACPRA - Syracuse Meeting, 1958-1960 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Administration Section, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Communications Development, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Development Section, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - General Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - General Program, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Medical Development, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Program Suggestions, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Public Relations, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Speakers, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Special Programs, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - ACPRA - Washington, D.C. Meeting - Thank You Letters, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 11)